A few days after my husband Paul was diagnosed with stage IV lung cancer,
بعدة عدة أيام من تشخيص زوجي (بول) بمرض سرطان الرئة المرحلة الرابعة،
we were lying in our bed at home,
كنا متمددين على السرير في المنزل،
and Paul said,
وقال بول:
"It's going to be OK."
"سيكون كل شيء ما يرام".
And I remember answering back,
وأتذكر أنني أجبته:
"Yes.
"نعم.
We just don't know what OK means yet."
ولكننا لا نعلم ما تعني (على ما يرام) بعد".
Paul and I had met as first-year medical students at Yale.
التقيت انا و بول كطلبة في السنة الأولى للطب في جامعة "يال"
He was smart and kind and super funny.
كان ذكيا ولطيفا ومرحا جدا.
He used to keep a gorilla suit in the trunk of his car,
كان يبقي بذلة (غوريلا) في حقيبة سيارته،
and he'd say, "It's for emergencies only."
ويقول:"إنها لحالات الطوارىء فقط".
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I fell in love with Paul as I watched the care he took with his patients.
وقعت في حب (بول) عندما شاهدت كيف يعتني بمرضاه.
He stayed late talking with them,
يبقي متأخرا يتحدث معهم،
seeking to understand the experience of illness
محاولا أن يفهم تجربة المرض
and not just its technicalities.
وليست فقط الأمور التقنية.
He later told me he fell in love with me
أخبرني لاحقا أنه وقع بحبي
when he saw me cry over an EKG of a heart that had ceased beating.
عندما شاهدني أبكي قرب جهاز تخطيط القلب لمريض توقف قلبه عن النبض .
We didn't know it yet,
لم نكن نعلم بهذا بعد،
but even in the heady days of young love,
ولكن حتى مع الأيام المتهورة لحبنا الشاب،
we were learning how to approach suffering together.
كنا نتعلم كيف نتغلب على المعاناة سوياً.
We got married and became doctors.
وتزوجنا واصبحنا أطباء.
I was working as an internist
وكنت أعمل كأخصائية طب باطني
and Paul was finishing his training as a neurosurgeon
و(بول) كان ينهي تدريبه كجراح أعصاب
when he started to lose weight.
عندما بدأ يفقد وزنه.
He developed excruciating back pain and a cough that wouldn't go away.
كان يعاني من ألم ظهر لا يطاق وسعال لا يتوقف.
And when he was admitted to the hospital,
وعندما أدخل إلى المستشفى،
a CT scan revealed tumors in Paul's lungs and in his bones.
أظهرت الأشعة المقطعية وجود أورام في رئتيه وعظامه.
We had both cared for patients with devastating diagnoses;
كنا نهتم لشأن المرضى الذين يتم تشخيصهم بأمراض خطرة،
now it was our turn.
والآن جاء دورنا.
We lived with Paul's illness for 22 months.
عشنا مع مرض (بول) لـ 22 شهرا.
He wrote a memoir about facing mortality.
وكتب مذكراته عن مواجهة الفناء.
I gave birth to our daughter Cady,
وأنجبت ابنتي (كادي)،
and we loved her and each other.
وأحببناها وأحببنا بعضنا.
We learned directly how to struggle through really tough medical decisions.
وتعلمنا مباشرة كيف نعاني مع القرارات الطبية الصعبة.
The day we took Paul into the hospital for the last time
اليوم الذي أخذوا فيه (بول) إلى المستشفى للمرة الأخيرة
was the most difficult day of my life.
كان أصعب يوم في حياتي.
When he turned to me at the end
وعندما التفت إلي في النهاية
and said, "I'm ready,"
وقال "أنا جاهز"،
I knew that wasn't just a brave decision.
علمت أنه لم يكن قراراً شجاعا فقط.
It was the right one.
بل كان القرار الصحيح.
Paul didn't want a ventilator and CPR.
لم يرد (بول) جهاز تنفس صناعي .
In that moment,
في تلك اللحظة،
the most important thing to Paul
كان الأمر الأكثر أهمية لـ(بول)
was to hold our baby daughter.
أن يحمل ابنتنا الصغيرة.
Nine hours later,
وبعد تسع ساعات،
Paul died.
مات (بول).
I've always thought of myself as a caregiver --
دوما ما فكرت في نفسي كشخص يقدم العناية للآخرين
most physicians do --
معظم الأطباء يفعلون هذا..
and taking care of Paul deepened what that meant.
وقد عمقت العناية بـ (بول) هذا المعنى في داخلي.
Watching him reshape his identity during his illness,
مشاهدته وهو يعيد تشكيل هويته أثناء مرضه،
learning to witness and accept his pain,
أن أتعلم كيف أشاهد ألمه وأتقبله،
talking together through his choices --
أن نتحدث مع بعضنا عن خياراته..
those experiences taught me
هذه التجارب علمتني
that resilience does not mean bouncing back to where you were before,
أن المرونة لا تعني العودة لما قبل حدوث الشيء،
or pretending that the hard stuff isn't hard.
أو التظاهر أن الأشياء الصعبة لم تكن صعبه.
It is so hard.
كان الأمر صعباً جداً.
It's painful, messy stuff.
ومؤلماً، هي أموراً فوضوية.
But it's the stuff.
ولكنها تلك الأمور.
And I learned that when we approach it together,
وتعلمت عندما نواجهها سوياً،
we get to decide what success looks like.
نقرر كيف سيبدو النجاح.
One of the first things Paul said to me after his diagnosis was,
أحد أول الأشياء التي قالها لي (بول) بعدما تم تشخصيه،
"I want you to get remarried."
"أريدك أن تتزوجي مجددا."
And I was like, whoa, I guess we get to say anything out loud.
وشعرت، أوه الآن بإمكاننا قول أي شيء بصوت مرتفع.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It was so shocking
كان الأمر صادماً.
and heartbreaking ...
ومحطماً للقلب...
and generous,
و كريماً،
and really comforting
ومريحاً جدا
because it was so starkly honest,
لأنه كان صادقا معي،
and that honesty turned out to be exactly what we needed.
وذلك الصدق أتضح أنه هو ما كنا نحتاجه.
Early in Paul's illness,
في بدايات مرض (بول)،
we agreed we would just keep saying things out loud.
أتفقنا على أن نقول الأشياء بصوت مرتفع.
Tasks like making a will,
مهمات مثل كتابة وصية،
or completing our advance directives --
أو إتمام أوامرنا المتقدمة...
tasks that I had always avoided --
مهمات طالما تجنبتها..
were not as daunting as they once seemed.
لم تكن امورا مرعبة كما كانت تبدوا .
I realized that completing an advance directive is an act of love --
ادركت أن إكمال توجيهات متقدمة هو فعل من افعال الحب..
like a wedding vow.
مثل عهود الزواج.
A pact to take care of someone,
عقد للعناية بأحدهم،
codifying the promise
تدوين الوعد
that til death do us part,
الذي ينص " حتى يفرقنا الموت،
I will be there.
سأكون معك".
If needed, I will speak for you.
إذا لزم الأمر، سأتحدث بالنيابة عنك.
I will honor your wishes.
سأحترم رغباتك.
That paperwork became a tangible part of our love story.
أصبح العمل الورقي جزئاً معقدا من قصة حبنا.
As physicians,
وكأطباء،
Paul and I were in a good position
كنا في موضع جيد
to understand and even accept his diagnosis.
لفهم وقبول تشخيص مرضه.
We weren't angry about it,
لم نكن غاضبين،
luckily,
وهذا من حظنا،
because we'd seen so many patients in devastating situations,
لأننا رأينا العديد من المرضى في وضع مؤلم،
and we knew that death is a part of life.
ونعلم أن الموت جزء من الحياة.
But it's one thing to know that;
ولكن معرفة هذا الأمر شيء مختلف،
it was a very different experience
كانت تجربة مختلفة جدا
to actually live with the sadness and uncertainty of a serious illness.
أن تعيش الحزن والمشاعر غير الأكيدة لمرض خطير.
Huge strides are being made against lung cancer,
الطب يتقدم بسرعة في مواجهة سرطان الرئة،
but we knew that Paul likely had months to a few years left to live.
ولكننا نعلم أن (بول) لم يمتلك سوى بضع سنوات ليعيشها.
During that time,
خلال ذلك الوقت،
Paul wrote about his transition from doctor to patient.
كتب (بول) عن تحوله من طبيب إلى مريض.
He talked about feeling like he was suddenly at a crossroads,
تكلم عن مشاعره كما لو كان فجأة عند مفترق الطريق،
and how he would have thought he'd be able to see the path,
وكيف كان يعتقد أنه سيرى الطريق،
that because he treated so many patients,
ولأنه عالج العديد من المرضى،
maybe he could follow in their footsteps.
ربما كان بإمكانه اتباع خطواتهم.
But he was totally disoriented.
ولكنه كان مشتتا تماما.
Rather than a path,
بدلا من طريق،
Paul wrote,
كتب (بول)
"I saw instead
"رأيت بدلا من هذا
only a harsh, vacant, gleaming white desert.
صحراء بيضاء قاسية وفارغة.
As if a sandstorm had erased all familiarity.
وكأن عاصفة رملية أزالت كل ما هو مألوف.
I had to face my mortality
كان علي مواجهة فنائي
and try to understand what made my life worth living,
ومحاولة فهم ما الذي جعلَ لحياتي قيمة للعيش
and I needed my oncologist's help to do so."
واحتجت لمساعدة طبيب الأورام لفهم هذا."
The clinicians taking care of Paul
الأخصائيون الذين اعتنوا بـ (بول)
gave me an even deeper appreciation for my colleagues in health care.
جعلوني أقدر زملائي في هذه المهنة بشكل أكبر.
We have a tough job.
كان لدينا عملا صعب.
We're responsible for helping patients have clarity around their prognoses
فنحن مسؤولون عن جعل المرضى يرون مرضهم بوضوح
and their treatment options,
وخيارات العلاج المتاحة لديهم،
and that's never easy, but it's especially tough
وهذا ليس سهلا، ولكنه صعب خصوصا
when you're dealing with potentially terminal illnesses like cancer.
عندما تتعامل مع مرض خطير مثل السرطان.
Some people don't want to know how long they have left,
البعض لا يريد معرفة كم تبقى له للعيش،
others do.
والبعض الآخر يود هذا.
Either way, we never have those answers.
وفي الحالتين، ليس لدينا أي من هذه الأجوبة.
Sometimes we substitute hope
بعض الأحيان نستبدل الأمل
by emphasizing the best-case scenario.
بالتشديد على أفضل سيناريو محتمل للمرض.
In a survey of physicians,
وفي دراسة أجريت على الأطباء،
55 percent said they painted a rosier picture
قال 55% منهم أنهم يعطون صورة أكثر وردية
than their honest opinion
من الرأي الحقيقي للحالة
when describing a patient's prognosis.
وهذا عندما يصفون التوقعات المحتملة للمرض.
It's an instinct born out of kindness.
وهذه غريزة تنتج من اللطف.
But researchers have found
ولكن الباحثون وجدوا
that when people better understand the possible outcomes of an illness,
أن الناس عندما يفهمون النتائج المحتملة لمرضهم،
they have less anxiety,
يكون خوفهم أقل،
greater ability to plan
ولديهم قدرة أكبر على التخطيط
and less trauma for their families.
وأيضا تكون الصدمة أقل على عائلاتهم.
Families can struggle with those conversations,
فالعائلات تعاني أثناء هذه الحوارات،
but for us, we also found that information immensely helpful with big decisions.
ولكن بالنسبة لنا، وجدنا أن هذه المعلومات تفيد في إتخاذ القرارات الكبرى.
Most notably,
بشكل أكبر،
whether to have a baby.
قرار إنجاب طفل.
Months to a few years meant Paul was not likely to see her grow up.
فالحياة لعدة أشهر إلى عدة سنوات تعني أن (بول) لن يراها تكبر.
But he had a good chance of being there for her birth
لكن كان لديه فرصة لرؤيتها عند ولادتها
and for the beginning of her life.
وفي بدايات عمرها.
I remember asking Paul
وأتذكر أني سألته
if he thought having to say goodbye to a child
إذا كان يظن أن توديع الأطفال
would make dying even more painful.
يجعل الموت أكثر ألما.
And his answer astounded me.
وقد أذهلتني إجابته.
He said,
حيث قال:
"Wouldn't it be great if it did?"
"أليس من الرائع لو حدث هذا؟"
And we did it.
وفعلنا ذلك.
Not in order to spite cancer,
ليس بالرغم من المرض،
but because we were learning
بل لأننا كنا نتعلم
that living fully means accepting suffering.
أن الحياة بشغف تعني أن تتقبل الألم.
Paul's oncologist tailored his chemo
وقد ضبط طبيب الأورام لـ(بول) جرعات الكيماوي
so he could continue working as a neurosurgeon,
حيث استمر يعمل كجراح أعصاب،
which initially we thought was totally impossible.
وقد ظننا هذا الأمر مستحيلا في البداية.
When the cancer advanced
ولكن عندما تقدم المرض
and Paul shifted from surgery to writing,
تحول (بول) من الجراحة للكتابة،
his palliative care doctor prescribed a stimulant medication
وقد وصف طبيبه اللطيف دوائاً محفزاً
so he could be more focused.
ليتمكن من التركيز.
They asked Paul about his priorities and his worries.
وقد سألوا (بول) عن أولوياته ومخاوفه.
They asked him what trade-offs he was willing to make.
وما الأشياء التي سيتمكن من التنازل عنها.
Those conversations are the best way to ensure
وهذه المحادثات هي أضمن طريقة
that your health care matches your values.
لتتوافق رعايتك الصحية مع قيمك.
Paul joked that it's not like that "birds and bees" talk
وضحك (بول) قائلا أن هذا ليس شبيها بحديث "النحل والطيور"
you have with your parents,
الذي تتحدثه مع والديك،
where you all get it over with as quickly as possible,
لتنتهون منه بأسرع وقت ممكن،
and then pretend it never happened.
ثم تتظاهرون أنه لم يحدث.
You revisit the conversation as things change.
فأنتم تعيدونه حين تتغير الأشياء.
You keep saying things out loud.
تقولون الأشياء بصوت مرتفع.
I'm forever grateful
وأنا ممتنة للأبد
because Paul's clinicians felt
لأن أطباء (بول) شعروا
that their job wasn't to try to give us answers they didn't have,
أنهم ليسوا بحاجة لمنحنا أجوبة هم لا يمتلكونها،
or only to try to fix things for us,
أو أن يقوموا بتعديل الأشياء لنا،
but to counsel Paul through painful choices ...
بل ليستشيروا (بول) في الخيارات المؤلمة...
when his body was failing but his will to live wasn't.
عندما كان جسده يتداعى ولكن رغبته في العيش ليست موجودة.
Later, after Paul died,
لاحقا، عندما مات (بول)،
I received a dozen bouquets of flowers,
تسلمت الكثير من الأزهار،
but I sent just one ...
ولكني أرسلت واحدة فقط...
to Paul's oncologist,
لطبيب الأورام الخاص بـ(بول)،
because she supported his goals
لأنها دعمت اهدافه
and she helped him weigh his choices.
وساعدته في وزن اختياراتهُ .
She knew that living means more than just staying alive.
كانت تعلم أن الحياة تعني أكثر من مجرد البقاء حيا.
A few weeks ago, a patient came into my clinic.
بعد عدة أسابيع، أتت مريضة لعيادتي.
A woman dealing with a serious chronic disease.
امرأة كانت تعاني من مرض مزمن.
And while we were talking about her life and her health care,
وعندما كنا نتكلم عن حياتها والرعاية الصحية المقدمة لها،
she said, "I love my palliative care team.
قالت: " أحب فريق الرعاية الصحية اللطيف.
They taught me that it's OK to say 'no'."
فقد أخبروني أنه بإمكاني أن أقول "لا"".
Yeah, I thought, of course it is.
نعم، لقد فكرت، بالطبع من الممكن.
But many patients don't feel that.
ولكن العديد من المرضى لا يشعرون بهذا.
Compassion and Choices did a study
قامت (كومباشن آند تشويسز) بإجراء دراسة
where they asked people about their health care preferences.
سألوا فيها الناس عن الرعاية الصحية المفضله لهم.
And a lot of people started their answers with the words
الكثير من الناس بدأو أجوبتهم قائلين
"Well, if I had a choice ..."
"حسنا، إذ كنت أملك الخيار..."
If I had a choice.
إذ كنت أمتلك خياراً.
And when I read that "if,"
عندما قرأت "إذ"،
I understood better
فهمت بشكل أفضل
why one in four people
لمَ شخص واحد من بين أربعة
receives excessive or unwanted medical treatment,
يخضع لعلاج طبي لا يرغبه،
or watches a family member receive excessive or unwanted medical treatment.
أو يشاهد أحد افراد عائلته يخضع لهذا.
It's not because doctors don't get it.
ليس لأن الأطباء لا يفهمون هذا.
We do.
نحن نفهم الأمر.
We understand the real psychological consequences
نحن نفهم العواقب النفسية الحقيقة
on patients and their families.
على المريض وعائلته.
The things is, we deal with them, too.
لكن الأمر هو أننا نتعرض لها أيضا.
Half of critical care nurses and a quarter of ICU doctors
نصف ممرضات العناية الحرجة وربع أطبائها
have considered quitting their jobs
فكروا في الإستقالة من عملهم
because of distress over feeling that for some of their patients,
بسبب الشعور المجهد نحو أحد المرضى،
they've provided care that didn't fit with the person's values.
لقد قدموا الرعاية التي لا تتفق مع قيم المريض.
But doctors can't make sure your wishes are respected
ولكن الأطباء ليسوا متأكدين من أن رغبتك يجب احترامها
until they know what they are.
حتى يتأكدوا منها.
Would you want to be on life support if it offered any chance of longer life?
هل تود أن تعيش على الأجهزة إذا توفرت لك فرصة حياة أطول؟
Are you most worried about the quality of that time,
ألست قلقا من جودة ذلك الوقت،
rather than quantity?
بدلا من مدته؟
Both of those choices are thoughtful and brave,
كل من هذه الخيارات شجاعة ومدروسة،
but for all of us, it's our choice.
ولكن لنا جميعاً، فهو خيارنا الخاص .
That's true at the end of life
وهذا حقيقي عند نهاية حياتك
and for medical care throughout our lives.
وللرعاية الصحية مدى حياتهم.
If you're pregnant, do you want genetic screening?
إذا كنتِ حاملا هل تودين أشعة للجينات؟
Is a knee replacement right or not?
القطع البديلة للركب مناسبة أو لا؟
Do you want to do dialysis in a clinic or at home?
هل تود القيام بغسيل الكلى في العيادة أو المنزل؟
The answer is:
الإجابة هي:
it depends.
يعتمد الأمر.
What medical care will help you live the way you want to?
هل تقدم لك الرعاية الصحية الحياة التي ترغبها؟
I hope you remember that question
أتمنى أن تتذكر ذلك السؤال
the next time you face a decision in your health care.
عندما تتخذ قراراً يخص رعايتك الصحية.
Remember that you always have a choice,
تذكر دائما أنك تملك الخيار،
and it is OK to say no to a treatment that's not right for you.
ولا بأس من قول كملة "لا" لعلاج لا يناسبك.
There's a poem by W.S. Merwin --
هناك قصيدة لـ (دبليو أس ميروين)...
it's just two sentences long --
تتكون من شطرين...
that captures how I feel now.
وتصف مشاعري الآن بالضبط.
"Your absence has gone through me
" غيابك رحل من خلالي
like thread through a needle.
مثل خيط دخل في خرم أبرة.
Everything I do is stitched with its color."
وكل ما أفعله، مطرز بهذا الخيط".
For me that poem evokes my love for Paul,
هذه القصيدة تعبر عن حبي لـ (بول)،
and a new fortitude
وقوة احتمالي
that came from loving and losing him.
الذي تكون من خلال حبي وخسارتي له.
When Paul said, "It's going to be OK,"
عندما قال (بول): "لا بأس، سيكون الأمر على ما يرام"
that didn't mean that we could cure his illness.
لم يعني الأمر أننا بإمكاننا علاجه.
Instead, we learned to accept both joy and sadness at the same time;
بدلا من هذا، تعلمنا قبوله بحزن وفرح في نفس الوقت.
to uncover beauty and purpose
لنكشف عن جمال وهدف هذه الحياة
both despite and because we are all born
التي بالرغم من ولادتنا
and we all die.
فكلنا سنموت.
And for all the sadness and sleepless nights,
ولكل تلك الليالي الحزينة والمؤرقة،
it turns out there is joy.
تبين أنه كان هناك فرح.
I leave flowers on Paul's grave
أترك الزهور على قبر (بول)
and watch our two-year-old run around on the grass.
وأشاهد ابنتي البالغة سنتين من العمر تجري حول العشب.
I build bonfires on the beach and watch the sunset with our friends.
أشعلت النيران على الشاطىء و شاهدت غروب الشمس مع أصدقائي.
Exercise and mindfulness meditation have helped a lot.
وقد ساعدتني التمارين والتأمل كثيرا.
And someday,
وفي يوماً ما،
I hope I do get remarried.
أتمنى أن أتزوج مجددا.
Most importantly, I get to watch our daughter grow.
الأهم من هذا، أني أشاهد ابنتي وهي تكبر.
I've thought a lot about what I'm going to say to her
لقد فكرت كثيرا في الكلام الذي يقولون لها
when she's older.
عندما تكبر.
"Cady,
"كادي،
engaging in the full range of experience --
بالإشتراك في الخبرات الكثيرة..
living and dying,
العيش والموت،
love and loss --
الحب والفقدان...
is what we get to do.
هو ما نفعله.
Being human doesn't happen despite suffering.
فلا يمكن أن تكون انساناً دون معاناة.
It happens within it.
بل ستكون معها
When we approach suffering together,
عندما نتعامل مع هذه المعاناة سويا،
when we choose not to hide from it,
عندما نختار أن لا نهرب منها،
our lives don't diminish,
فحياتنا لا تتناقص،
they expand."
بل تمتد".
I've learned that cancer isn't always a battle.
تعلمت أن مرض السرطان ليس دائما معركة.
Or if it is,
إذا كان كذلك،
maybe it's a fight for something different than we thought.
فهي معركة لشيء مختلف عما نفكر به.
Our job isn't to fight fate,
فعملنا ليس أن نحارب القدر،
but to help each other through.
بل أن نساعد الآخرين أثناءه.
Not as soldiers
ليس كجنود
but as shepherds.
بل كرعاة.
That's how we make it OK,
هكذا يكون الأمر لا بأس به،
even when it's not.
حتى عندما لا يكون كذلك.
By saying it out loud,
عندما نقولها بصوت مرتفع،
by helping each other through ...
عندما نساعد بعضنا أثناءه...
and a gorilla suit never hurts, either.
فلبس الغوريلا لا يؤذي أبدا.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)